<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>
        BASIC blog full text feed    </title>
        <link href="/blog/atom.xml" rel="self" />
    
        <link href="/"/>
    
        
    <updated>2014-10-06T21:23:31Z</updated>

    <id>/blog/atom.xml/</id>

            <entry>
            <title type="html">UK Data Science MSc Courses</title>
            <author><name>Lakshmi Vyasarajan</name></author>
            <link href="/blog/uk-data-science-masters.html"/>
            <updated>2014-08-29T18:00:00Z</updated>
            <published>2014-08-29T18:00:00Z</published>
            <id>/blog/uk-data-science-masters.html</id>
                        <category   scheme="/blog/tags"
                        term="teaching"
                        label="Teaching" />
                        <category   scheme="/blog/tags"
                        term="data science"
                        label="Data Science" />
            
            <content type="html">
                                &lt;p&gt;A review of MSc Data Science courses in the &lt;span class=&#34;caps&#34;&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt;.
&lt;h3&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you want to be a Data Scientist do you? And who could blame you, with big companies
eager to recruit on the top salary scales and big science needing you to save the planet.
But how do you become a Data&amp;nbsp;Scientist? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data Science is a new field, and the definition is still vague. Its a
mix of computing, statistics, database work, graphics, &lt;span class=&#34;caps&#34;&gt;AI&lt;/span&gt; and general
knowledge. Cynically its said to be &amp;#8220;Statistics done on a Mac&amp;#8221;. The
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_science&#34;&gt;Wikipedia article&lt;/a&gt; has
more on the great debate as to whether the term has any meaning at&amp;nbsp;all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought it might be informative to see what Data Science meant in the
eyes of &lt;span class=&#34;caps&#34;&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt; university MSc course convenors. So I did a search for
&lt;a href=&#34;https://duckduckgo.com/?q=UK+MSc+Data+Science&#34;&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;span class=&#34;caps&#34;&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt; MSc Data Science&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt; on DuckDuckGo
and this is the summary what I&amp;#8217;d found. I also had a quick look at some other major
universities that didn&amp;#8217;t show up in the search - and could find no sign of
MSc programmes in Data Science
from Oxford, Cambridge, Manchester or Liverpool on their web sites. However
I don&amp;#8217;t claim this is a complete list of Data Science MSc courses in the &lt;span class=&#34;caps&#34;&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt;,
just the ones I found. Please suggest any corrections or criticisms by posting a
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/spacedman/barry/issues&#34;&gt;github issue&lt;/a&gt; on this&amp;nbsp;site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Methodology&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For each of the MSc schemes I found, I recorded its full title and the
department or departments which hosted it. I looked at the syllabus and
noted which particular software systems and topics were listed. The order 
here is basically the order of the search results. Links to the courses
are as of August 2014, and may not point to the same course
when you read&amp;nbsp;this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some course programmes didn&amp;#8217;t mention any specific software packages,
but stressed the syllabus&amp;nbsp;topics. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that I did this search and summary in August 2014. This is perhaps not the best
time to get up-to-date information. Most of these syllabi were for October 2014 entry
and were probably already closed to entry, and could well be in the process of updating
for next year. Always check the university web site for up-to-date&amp;nbsp;information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Overall&amp;nbsp;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One-year, full-time taught MSc&amp;nbsp;courses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Entry requirement is usually a degree in Comp Sci, Maths, or&amp;nbsp;Science&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Course structures are mostly three terms of lectures plus summer&amp;nbsp;project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most MSc programmes are run purely by computing or computer science&amp;nbsp;departments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If a syllabus mentioned any programming languages, R was always one of&amp;nbsp;them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python and Java were also well&amp;nbsp;represented&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open Source software is dominant, both in languages and&amp;nbsp;systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Big Data and Machine Learning are emphasised on most&amp;nbsp;syllabi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadoop and NoSQL technologies are&amp;nbsp;common&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Individual&amp;nbsp;Courses&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.city.ac.uk/courses/postgraduate/data-science-msc&#34;&gt;City University&amp;nbsp;London&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;City&amp;#8217;s MSc is run across four departments - Informatics, Maths, CompSci and Engineering.
They list a wide range of software including the proprietary Matlab and &lt;span class=&#34;caps&#34;&gt;SPSS&lt;/span&gt; packages,
as well as C++ and &lt;span class=&#34;caps&#34;&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;programming. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to machine learning and big data, their syllabus also includes modules
on research methods and professional issues in data&amp;nbsp;science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gold.ac.uk/pg/msc-data-science/&#34;&gt;Goldsmiths University of&amp;nbsp;London&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Goldsmiths the Data Science MSc course is run by Computing. When boiled down to software and topics
it seems quite similar to City&amp;#8217;s course. One of their optional modules is in &amp;#8220;Music
Information&amp;nbsp;Retrieval&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.brunel.ac.uk/courses/postgraduate/data-science-and-analytics-msc&#34;&gt;Brunel&amp;nbsp;University&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brunel&amp;#8217;s course, run by the Computer Science dept, is called &amp;#8220;MSc Data Science and Analytics&amp;#8221;, perhaps reflecting the 
legacy of &amp;#8220;Business Analytics&amp;#8221; that Data Science may have inherited. The business
analytical nature of the course is reflected in the fact that it seems to be almost
a one-year course in &lt;span class=&#34;caps&#34;&gt;SAS&lt;/span&gt;, a proprietary statistics package widely used in the business
analytics field. Students have an option to obtain a &lt;span class=&#34;caps&#34;&gt;SAS&lt;/span&gt; certification as part of the&amp;nbsp;course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The syllabus naturally has a business and innovation focus, with a project management module
and a data management/business intelligence&amp;nbsp;module.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uel.ac.uk/postgraduate/specs/data-science/&#34;&gt;University of East&amp;nbsp;London&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The MSc in Data Science at &lt;span class=&#34;caps&#34;&gt;UEL&lt;/span&gt; is run by the Centre for
Geo-Information Studies. Although they don&amp;#8217;t mention any programming
languages or software systems, I don&amp;#8217;t think the practical sessions
could be done without some programming&amp;nbsp;training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a strong emphasis on statistical analysis rather than
computing systems to the syllabus. It also includes a module on spatial data&amp;nbsp;analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.macs.hw.ac.uk/cs/pgcourses/ds.htm&#34;&gt;Heriot Watt&amp;nbsp;University&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heriot Watt&amp;#8217;s MSc Data Science programme looks like an advanced Computer Science
course with a big data slant to it. Any mention of any named software 
is hard to find, even in the detailed course &lt;span class=&#34;caps&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt; documents. Several of the 
modules have prerequisites such as Artificial Intelligence. Statistics only
appears in the Data Mining&amp;nbsp;module.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gla.ac.uk/postgraduate/taught/datascience/&#34;&gt;University of&amp;nbsp;Glasgow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Staying up in Scotland, the Data Science MSc at the University of Glasgow
is run by the Comp Sci department. Its computing origins show up in the long
list of optional modules from the whole CompSci field, such as &lt;span class=&#34;caps&#34;&gt;AI&lt;/span&gt;, Cyber Security, and 
&lt;span class=&#34;caps&#34;&gt;HCI&lt;/span&gt;. The course web site has a huge &amp;#8220;Big Data&amp;#8221; signpost. There&amp;#8217;s no mention of 
languages or systems, so its a guess as to what precisely you&amp;#8217;d learn, but that might
not be a&amp;nbsp;problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lancaster.ac.uk/data-science/&#34;&gt;Lancaster&amp;nbsp;University&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disclosure: I work in Health and Medicine at Lancaster University, but have had no
role in this course. I do know some of the people who devised and deliver&amp;nbsp;it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course is spread over three departments - most of it is done by Maths and Stats 
together with Computing Science, with the Lancaster Environment Centre giving students
the option to do a project in the environment. This syllabus has the strongest statistical
emphasis of any Data Science course, with modules in the basics of statistical theory
as well as methods. Students are taught R and Java, because these seem to be the two
preferred languages of the two main&amp;nbsp;departments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coventry.ac.uk/course-structure/2014/faculty-of-engineering-and-computing/postgraduate/data-science-and-computational-intelligence-msc/&#34;&gt;Coventry&amp;nbsp;University&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Coventry, the MSc in Data Science and Computational Intelligence is hosted
by the Comp Sci department. The syllabus extends to business intelligence and 
fuzzy logic alongside the almost ubiquitous data mining and big data modules.
There&amp;#8217;s no mention of any languages or software&amp;nbsp;systems. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although some courses listed here need a computing degree for entry, this 
course accepts students with a maths or other science&amp;nbsp;qualification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.royalholloway.ac.uk/computerscience/coursefinder/mscdatascienceandanalytics.aspx&#34;&gt;Royal Holloway University of&amp;nbsp;London&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disclosure: I did my undergraduate degree here. But that was a long time ago
and I have no contacts there now. But I&amp;#8217;m sure the campus and location is still&amp;nbsp;beautiful!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The MSc here is in Data Science and Analytics, run by the Comp Sci department.
They will teach R and Matlab, and big data technologies including Hadoop and MongoDB. 
The syllabus has substantial programming content, including modules on
programming for data analysis and object-oriented programming. The possible specialisms
include&amp;nbsp;finance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sheffield.ac.uk/is/pgt/courses/data_science&#34;&gt;University of&amp;nbsp;Sheffield&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Sheffield Data Science MSc is brought to you by the joint effort of 
the Information School and Social Sciences. This perhaps explains the mention
of &lt;span class=&#34;caps&#34;&gt;SPSS&lt;/span&gt; in their syllabus alongside R. The course modules include
visualisation and database design together with less quantitative options
in business information, social media, and information&amp;nbsp;governance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dundee.ac.uk/postgraduate/courses/data_science_msc.htm&#34;&gt;University of&amp;nbsp;Dundee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in Scotland, the Data Science MSc at Dundee is another course
run by the Computing department. They teach R and Java, as well as Erlang.
The syllabus seems business-oriented, including a module on business information
systems, and strong database focus, and visualisation. There&amp;#8217;s also an advanced
statistics module alongside the usual data mining&amp;nbsp;module.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www2.warwick.ac.uk/study/postgraduate/courses/depts/compsci/taught/data&#34;&gt;University of&amp;nbsp;Warwick&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warwick&amp;#8217;s course is an MSc in Data Analytics. Run by Comp Sci, it
also encompasses sensor networks, signal and image processing, &lt;span class=&#34;caps&#34;&gt;IT&lt;/span&gt; 
security and other modules not often found in Data Science courses.
The languages and systems they use isn&amp;#8217;t&amp;nbsp;given.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.swansea.ac.uk/postgraduate/taught/medicine/msc-health-data-science/&#34;&gt;Swansea University/Prifysgol&amp;nbsp;Abertawe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The department of Medicine at Swansea offer an MSc in Health Data Science.
In this syllabus the modules are all targeted towards applications in 
healthcare and medical data analysis. The course includes Linked Data
Analysis and Visualisation. Alongside business and science applications,
health is another big growth area for data scientists as more health
data is routinely&amp;nbsp;collected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;            </content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html">This New Site</title>
            <author><name>Lakshmi Vyasarajan</name></author>
            <link href="/blog/newblog-post.html"/>
            <updated>2014-01-08T18:00:00Z</updated>
            <published>2014-01-08T18:00:00Z</published>
            <id>/blog/newblog-post.html</id>
                        <category   scheme="/blog/tags"
                        term="web"
                        label="Web" />
                        <category   scheme="/blog/tags"
                        term="news"
                        label="News" />
            
            <content type="html">
                                &lt;p&gt;My home page has been unchanged for years. This is&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great isn&amp;#8217;t&amp;nbsp;it?&lt;/p&gt;            </content>
        </entry>
    </feed>